All
right. All right. It is April 7th, 2025.
This is going to be active inference
stream
12.1 cerebrum case enabled reasoning
engine with basian representations for
unified modeling. I've started first to
make a GitHub push to the GitHub repo
active inference
institute
cerebrum and that is now
live and here in
cursor I'm running
the render
script render markdown which calls the
script render
mermaids which takes this markdown file
and all of these 15 figure level
markdown files and the math and the
novel case
appendix and is going to result in a
PDF. The
PDF looks like
this. In this stream, we're going to go
through the PDF and talk about probably
a bunch more depending
on who shows up.
Um, I'm going to finish flipping through
the PDF. Then we will see where the PDF
generation is at. And then we will go
through this. This should be super
interesting.
Um, conclusion appendix one
math appendix
2 novel cases. All right.
The generation will finish
soon. It renders each of the 15 mermaid
uh diagram
figures which look like
this
into figures that look like that and
then inserts them into the markdown. All
right, PDF generated. It generates
cerebrum.pdf. So that's the newly
rendered
version
and I'll push it and then let us get
into the
topic. I also just pushed this to
Zenotto
and looking forward
to where we go from here. So, we're all
pushed on the
repo. Let's look at the paper and go
through some of the sections. All
right, I'll read the abstract
first. This paper introduces case
enabled reasoning engine with basian
representations for unified modeling.
Cerebrum. Cerebrum is a synthetic
intelligence framework that integrates
linguistic case systems with cognitive
scientific principles to describe,
design, and deploy generative models in
an expressive fashion. By treating
models as case bearing entities that can
play multiple contextual roles like
declinable nouns, cerebrum establishes a
formal linguistic type calculus for
cognitive model use, relationships, and
transformations. The cerebrum framework
uses structures from category theory and
modeling techniques related to the free
energy principle in describing and
utilizing models across
contexts. Cerebrum addresses the growing
complexity in computational and
cognitive modeling systems eg generative
decentralized agentic intelligences by
providing structured representations of
model ecosystems that align with lexical
ergonomics scientific principles and
operational processes. and we will
probably push to another version by the
end of the stream. So, we'll fix a few
different things that we can see along
the
way. Describing and
utilizing
models across
contexts. Okay, continuing to overview.
Cerebrum implements a comprehensive
approach to cognitive systems modeling
by applying linguistic case systems to
model management. This framework treats
cognitive models as entities that can
exist in different cases as in a
morphologically rich language based on
their functional role within an
intelligence production workflow. This
enables more structured representation
of model relationships and
transformations. And the code to
generate this paper and further open
source development from this 1.0
milestone is available at this GitHub
repo and that's what we'll be pushing to
and using during this
stream.
Okay, background sections. First
background sections on cognitive systems
modeling. The second background section
is about active inference. The third
background segment is about linguistic
case systems and I'm going to read this
one because this might be the one that's
the wild card. However, this is the crux
and as a first language English speaker,
as we'll discuss, there are some
interesting ways of having
the cases a bit more silent in English
than some other languages like Russian
and Latin and other things that will
probably end up on Wikipedia to find out
today. So I'm going to read this
linguistic case
section. Linguistic case systems
represent grammatical relationships
between words among words through
morphological marking. Case systems
operate as morphos syntactic interfaces
between semantics and syntax encoding
contextualized relationship types rather
than just or in addition to just
sequential ordering. This inherent
relationality makes case systems
powerful abstractions for modeling
complex dependencies and transformations
between conceptual entities. Cases under
consideration here include nominative,
subject, accusative,
object, dative, recipient, genative,
possessor, instrumental, tool, locative,
location, and ablative origin. All
serving different functional roles
within sentence structure.
language. Um, English has largely lost
its morphological case system. The
underlying case relationships still
exist and are expressed through word
order and prepositions. For example, in
the cat chased the mouse, the nominative
case is marked by position, subject
before verb rather than morphology.
While in I gave him the book, the dative
case is marked by the preposition to and
word order. This demonstrates that the
semantics/chemiosis/pragmatics of case
relationships are fundamental to
language structure even when not overtly
marked morphologically eg expressed in
writing or spoken
language. Section 134 intelligence case
management systems. So, this sort of
speaks to the pun at the heart of this,
which is case management, which might be
for like a help ticket or a research
inquiry or any other kind of case
management. It's a bit of a hinge with
the linguistic case systems. So,
coincidence, but enough of a connection
and gap there to have the linguistic
case system be the theory and the
category theory and some of the
transformations that are going to be
going into And then combining this with
more of an operational layer and
thinking about what are the different
roles that generative models really do
play in different kinds of case
managements seen more from an
operational
view. Okay. Section 1.4 towards
languages for generative modeling. I'm
going to read the section. The active
inference community has extensively
explored numerous adjectal modifications
of the base framework including for
example deep affective branching time
quantum mortal structured inference
among others. Each adjectival prefixed
variant emphasizes specific
architectural aspects or extensions of
the core formalism. Building on this
cerebrum focuses on a wider range of
linguistic formalism. For example, in
this paper, declenional semantics rather
than adjectival modifications or
prefixing. In this first cerebrum paper,
there is an emphasis on the declenional
related to declining aspects of
generative models as noun-like entities
separate from adjectival qualification.
This approach aligns with category
theoretic approaches to linguistics
where morphisms between objects
formalize grammatical relationships and
transformations. Many such cases by
applying formal case grammar to
generative models. Cerebrum extends and
transposes structured modeling
approaches to ecosystems of shared
intelligence while preserving the
underlying partitioned, flexible,
variational, composable, interfacial,
interactive, empirical, applicable,
communicable semantics.
1.5 The intersection of cognitive
systems modeling, active
inference, linguistic case systems, and
intelligence
production. 1.6 methods and
materials. The cerebrum framework was
developed as part of a broader synthetic
intelligence framework combining
linguistic theory, cognitive science,
category theory, and operations
research. Key approaches included
linguistic formalization, category
theoretic mapping and algorithmic
implementation. Figure one here are
those foundation domains flowing into
cerebrum. The functional and the
processional elements of the
framework. Different
features and system
outcomes leading to enhanced model
management.
Core concept 1.7 cognitive models as
case bearing entities. Just as nouns in
morphologically rich languages can take
different forms based on their
grammatical function, cognitive models
in cerebrum can exist in different
states or
cases depending on how they relate to
other models or processes within the
system. Figure two illustrates this
linguistic parallel.
zoom
in. So
here provocatively laid out
generatively on the diagonal are the
cases and how they'll be
abbreviated. Nominative, accusative,
dative, generative, genative,
instrumental, locative, ablative,
invocative.
Up and to the right are examples with a
cat as noun. Down and to the left are
the
analogous functional roles and sort of
parts of speech
as in describing to the generative model
which is what the focus of this
is. Okay. going into a bit more detail
about what do these different cases do?
What is the point of being able
to decline a generative model like a
noun into these different
cases? So here is three clusters of
cases. On the left are the genative and
the ablative case. And ablative as it as
its name sort of even suggests was uh
relatively earlier
lost. And so it's uh not always seen but
and you know it's these things are just
popping up and down in in different
languages really interesting ways and
gener genative which that sort of pun
with genative and generative is going to
come back. Um here the generations
coming from something or the possession
of
something the locative instrumental
invocative here are clustered with the
contextual cases. So these and also the
primary cases with doing the the direct
agent doing the action like with
nominative like the cat jumps over the
moon or in the accusative or the dative
being the recipient of action.
So different cases that might be used
linguistically in describing like the
source or origin
like is that your guitar from where did
that guitar come
from? It was brought from here. It is
possessed of this
person. Those are uh sentences that
would be about some sort of material
noun that might use these different
cases to provide those functions. And
here it's like a analogy extended into
talking about joint distribution
generative
models. Here's a table with all of the
cases that are going to be
considered. the abbreviation the full
name of the case the function and the
example.
So nominative model is active agent. Cat
jumps over the moon. Model generates
predictions. Model does something. This
is sort of the the base
model just declaring the form that's in
the
dictionary. Uh accusive accusative and
dative. This is model as object and
recipient. And these relate to processes
that are inputting or targeting the
model like some method applied to the
model or
something from another source being
received by the model.
Genative, the output of the model,
something that comes from the
inferences and the ablative, possibly
very similar or redundant or not needed
in situations, but related to basically
the difference between the ablative
attribution and the
generative instrumental. This is uh
possibly a very common case for using
when talking about a model analysis
performed with something like the
implementation of a model as a
model and the vocative model as
addressable
entity. For example, hey model X all the
different names that these chat
assistants have. So calling something by
name direct invocation task
initialization and documentation
reference point like referring to a
parameter as its parameter in a system
or or something like that. Maybe there's
different you know
subtypes. Um,
okay.
1.9 a preliminary
example. Thank you for your question,
Dong. I will get to it. I want to get
through the paper mostly in one sweep
and then happy to look at your question
and any other questions people have. All
right. 1.9. A preliminary example of a
case bearing model homeostatic
thermostat.
Consider a cognitive model of a
homeostatic thermostat that perceives
room temperature with a thermometer and
regulates temperature through connected
heating and cooling systems. This is
kind of the classic
model simple
homeostatic. In nominative case, the
thermostat model actively generates
temperature predictions and dispatches
control signals functioning as the
primary agent in the temperature
regulation process. So that's kind of
like an operational
utilization or generic situation
considered holistically version that's
in the
dictionary. When placed in accusative
case, the same model has become the
object of optimization processes with
its parameters being updated based on
prediction errors between expected and
actual temperature
readings. Change your mind, change the
world. In data case, the thermostat
model receives environmental temperature
streams. These can also be ongoing
simultaneously which is going to be uh
gotten to later with the precision
modulation and occupant comfort
preferences as inputs. The generative
case transforms the model into a
generator of temperature regulation
reports and system performance
analytics. So basically synthetic data
generation or generative AI like
generative AI when an instrumental case
the thermostat serves as computational
tool implementing control algorithms for
other systems requiring temperature
management. It's being used like a
tool. The locative case reconfigures the
model to represent the contextual
environment in which temperature
regulation
occurs. Modeling building thermal
properties. So perhaps locationational
topics or discussing something within
the model as a location like model as
place. Finally, in a blade of case, the
thermostat functions as the origin of
historical temperature data and control
decisions, providing causal explanations
for current thermal
conditions. This single cognitive model
thus assumes dramatically different
functional roles while maintaining its
core identity as a
thermostat. Figure four, generative
model integration in intelligence case
management. First place, a good render
from above. Here's just different stages
and different ways in which stages of
research and intelligence work relates
to different case aspects being
highlighted. 110 declinability of active
inference generative models. At the core
of cerebrum lies the concept of
declinability. the capacity for
generative models to assume different
morphological and functional roles
through case transformations mirroring
the declenion patterns of nouns in
morphologically rich languages unlike
traditional approaches where models
maintain fixed roles or variable roles
defined by analytical pipelines. So
which is to say that there's some
process by which like well now we're
going to specify it declaratively then
we're going to do this thing that
updates it then we're going to generate
some data from it then we're going to do
this thing that updates it then we're
going to generate some data then we're
going to give a final updating and then
we're going to use it as a tool. Some
process like that which is just defined
procedurally here gives a more
expressive layer on top of what even
that is and expands out and generalizes
what that space of procedures is
materialized
from. So what are those changes that
happen for generative models?
It's not necessarily that some suffix
like in the case of a noun the end of
the noun might change and there's
probably different ways this happens in
different languages. So what is it that
actually changes by analogy in when a
generative model is actually declined
into these different ways cases. So one
functional interfaces could change what
is being received andor
transmitted parameters across
patterns. So what kinds of parameters
are in play? Prior distributions could
be a different
prior. Maybe if depending on whether
it's playing one role or another,
something is more or less likely to
happen. Update
dynamics. In what ways does the model
update if at all? And perhaps different
computational resourcing also including
different thresholds or approaches. So
one approach being there's a 0ero to one
waiting like an attention or a precision
on all these cases in play at once or
one could have a one hot and some kind
of other rule for just only computing
one of these settings and then depending
on how you parameterize what each of
these settings would be. It's not that
receiving and updating has a higher
computational cost than being used to
make an action selection, but there
could be a setting where receiving and
updating is very simple. There could be
a setting where that's very complex.
Same as for action selection. So what
happens
when the generative model gets this
modification here? Table two describes
how each of the
cases different changes could happen
parametrically including structure
learning and what happens at the
interface of the
model. How does that relate to a
precision weighted generalized approach
kind of like the Sanv Smith
approach? Consider a perceptionoriented
generative model M with parameters of
theta didn't
render. Let's fix that.
The theta for parameters does not render
update
the so it is plain
text data and check anywhere else that
might be
relevant. So M is the joint distribution
generative
model. Here's another list of those
cases being used in different
ways. The vocative
case voke represents a unique functional
role where models serve as directly
addressable entities within a model
ecosystem. Unlike other cases that focus
on data processing or transformational
aspects, the vocative case specifically
optimizes a model for name based
recognition and command reception. This
has particular relevance in synthetic
intelligence environments where models
must be selectively activated or woken
up through explicit address similar to
how humans are called by name to gain
their attention. The vocative case
maintains specialized interfaces for
handling direct commands, documentation
references, and initialization requests.
In practical application, models
invocative case might serve as
conversational agents awaiting
activation, document reference points
within technical specifications or
system components that remain dormant
until explicitly addressed. This pattern
mimics the v linguistic vocative case
where a noun is used in direct address
as in hey Siri or okay Google activation
phrases for digital assistance creating
a natural bridging pattern between human
language interaction and model
orchestration.
This systematic pattern of
transformations constitutes a complete
declenion paradigm for cognitive models
using precision modulation to fulfill
diverse functional roles while
maintaining their core
identity. Now pivoting from that
linguistic case
focus to thinking about the role of
those different cases in model
workflows.
that is in figure five and six. So
here's an example of how
one kind of generative model might move
through these different cases. So first
a a model specified in nominative it
processes data at as a direct object.
It's used to generate source synthetic
data. Then it it is the the sender andor
receiver of information at different
levels from the sort of fine-tuning and
context layer here like a feedback
between the analyst and the results at
this
layer or at the second layer. a feedback
involving data selection or attention
andor even reaching back to the model's
structure. Here's figure six more
explicitly
in in the context
of the intelligence production workflow.
So here's data collection, gathering of
raw data used as an as
instrumentally activating some kind of
model. This is just one example
motif processing and and defining the
model providing locationational
situational
context generating and evaluating data
with context changes.
Then generating from the refined model,
deploying the refined
model one possible
pipeline. Figure 7 has some of the
category theory connections and seeds
with that are mainly drawn from other
research in the category theory of
linguistic case. So tenative just like
all of it. Figure
eight more types of
transformations. So for example, let's
start with the nominative with the sort
of agentic
framing. There might be some kind of
transformation like
objectification that combines with
external data to result in a well
formatted processed model. In the
accusative
case, some type of targeting from or to
that transformed object could bring it
into being addressed or being used as a
actor or recipient or whatever the
analogy is in the datative.
Then in the
generative different kinds of
cycles, figure 9 goes into a sort
of esoteric but interesting aspect of
linguistics. Again, something that's
really implicit in English or it was
hard to even sort of think about how how
different this was, but that's kind of
the cool part about
language. So, morphos syntactic
alignment and the difference between the
erative absolutive patient oriented
modeling and the nominative accusative,
the
agentoriented moni modeling. And the
reason why this box isn't the same color
is there might be some operations that
differ between these two or might be a
dual representation. But from the point
of view of something downstream in the
process, that is an example of a kind of
morphos syntactic
difference that perhaps one
underlying situational reference source
could be expressed in a arrogative
absolutive frame or language or in a
nominative accusative.
1.14 goes into more detail into
implementations and how this could play
a role with the different cases being
relevant at different stages of
implementation.
It's pretty interesting to think about
how different kinds of resourcing and
costs of different operations just like
how with a transformer LLM there might
be a different amount of computations
required to train it for the first time
to fine-tune it to fill its context
window
to just do the embedding to generate
data. All these kinds of things have
different computational costs and they
have different scalings and that is
going to depend a lot on the state space
of the model. But it also depends given
the state space of the model about all
of these more pipeline scale modeler
degrees of freedom like how do we
actually host the data and all those
kinds of training and how many times do
we actually do different steps. So
here's one in figure 11. One example
again of
that
some model is used in raw data
collection.
A model is
activated through the
vocative. And these different steps can
happen and and possibly another or
multiple cases of the very same
generative model or different models
that are in different cases. Just like a
given step of a story or a given
situation might even in the same
sentence have just one case or it could
have multiple cases in a compound
sentence because it could be like the
guitar of that person was used by this
person to do this leading to this at
this location. All those kinds of
sentences that that happen.
another visualization just with a
different clustering but similar to 11
and 12. And we maybe we can update
12.
Um here's how linguistics, cognitive
systems modeling, active inference, and
intelligence production make
contributions and also relate to
cerebrum. Kind of revisiting that
All right, 1.18 related work. So here's
an important epistemic disclaimer.
Cerebrum builds upon several research
traditions while offering a novel
synthesis. In this first paper, there
are no specific works linked or cited.
Later work will provide more detail and
reference in derivation. The work stands
transparently on the shoulders of
nestmates and so is presented initially
as a speculative design checkpoint in
the development of certain cognitive
modeling
practices. There's cognitive
architectures backgrounds everything
with knowledge modeling cognitive
architectures active inference etc.
Um figure
13, here's how one model might relate to
um different utilizations within the
same active inference predictive
processing
hierarchy. So here's a model being used
in different cases with a top down
prediction and the bottom up
errors. Here's describing different
kinds of aspects of the
agent mapping the active inference
ontology to different cases that it is
in or could be said
in and one way to possibly implement
that is precision weighted message
passing and free energy minimization. So
figure 14 goes into a little bit more of
that. So the whole box is yellow again
to have a sort of symbolism like from
the outside. This could be a multiple
dispatch and it it it might matter how
different message passing plays out. But
there's also another level where it can
be just core strained to that level at
least conceptually if not in the
implementation dispatch. So here's the
instrumental, nominative, accusative,
dative, genative, and
vocative, and how they might connect to
the error and
prediction
motif of a
two-layer hierarchical predictive
processing. So just different kinds of
modes might relate to different
modulations of features of um a
hierarchical predictive processing
architecture. So kind of like different
positions of the hand on the guitar
could lead to resonating
uh simatics vibrations different way.
15 is the model case calculus framework.
So here's some more bringing together of
how the mo here with a subscript
notation for different
cases showing how different functional
roles and cases relate to
subscript
changes which can be applied through to
to be determined to be uh
invented/discovered. Not necessarily
infinite or open-ended, but certainly
definite calculus laws like what kinds
of model transformations and
concatenations and composabilities are
valid within which understandings of
case and which ones also perhaps by
definition perhaps by implication are
invalid given a case approach in a
language.
more background references could be find
uh could be found with category theory,
active inference, linguistic
computing. Okay. 1.19 practical
applications. Here's a few situations
where this could be really practical to
apply. One is in model pipeline design
and optimization and the resource
optimization. As sort of mentioned
earlier here might be given some
constraints on resources of different
kinds what kinds of cases one might be
expecting to want their model to be
optimized to be in. For example, let's
just think by analogy to like an LLM.
Let's just say that there's a few
architectures that have the same score
on a benchmark, but one of them is 10
times more expensive in RAM or storage
or CPU or money or whatever it is to
train, but then it's cheaper to run. Or
it's cheaper to train, but it's more
expensive to run or it's able to have a
larger context window, but it costs more
to do this or it has some other
trade-off or something like that. So on
those parareto optimal sort of
constraints manifolds within empirical
computational finite
space just from a pragmatic perspective
resource
allocation that might be able to guide
what
features at the meta modeling level. How
do we want to think about it? What
functional roles even matter to
benchmark? What tests should be written
around what kind of functional roles for
what kind of
artifacts? Table six, some cross-domain
integration patterns. So just sort of
like associating differently and more
how these cases can be used. even one
domain unsurprisingly
um like reasoning might have multiple
cases deployed just like if we were
going to talk about somebody in a
library and they're engaged in
perception. So it's
like that might use a lot of sentences
involving nominative or accusative like
they looked at the book and so that
might put the book as the recipient of
action in the accusative and so the same
type of agent and
artifactbased ecosystem of share
intelligence model that kind of
describing perceptual gestalt aspects
whatever components might involve a lot
of like active agents and recipient
agents. Talking about reasoning might be
talking a lot with instrumentality and
context. Talking about planning might be
about
goals of an
agent like Tilios and the ablative
history in terms of where where did it
ablate from like what was removed or
what was generated. This is a case we
can look more into or write a new
section on what is the oblate of me or
something like that. And in the action
case, there might be active agents and
and recipients kind of like the
accusative 1.19.5.
This is describing some ways that this
kind of semantic labeling on a knowledge
graph could be used to to structure just
like if it were going to be a graph of
the food web or ecosystem of some region
in the sort of hyperlink style or
unstructured edges like
obsidian. It might be ambiguous like
well what does this edge mean? doesn't
mean it's a type of and and there's
exactly that which is what structured
ontological approaches exist for and
constraint either interpreting those
linguistically andor constraining the
edge types that are in play. two kinds
of linguistic assertions is possibly a a
pretty parsimmonious and aergonomic way
to do it because it would reflect the
kinds of expressions people would say
about the
ecosystem. 1.19.6 Six, emergent
behaviors in model
collectives. When multiple case bearing
models interact within an ecosystem,
emergent collective behaviors arise from
their case-driven interactions analogous
to how linguistic communities develop
shared understanding through dialogue.
So that could kind of get into some of
these linguistic
features
in discourse community, not just loading
up context windows of each other and
then continuing the conversation, which
works really well in the prompt
engineering multi- aent modeling
approach. Uh really common with LLMs,
agent laboratory, Andrew Pashchet's
work, all that kind of stuff.
Th this is getting a little bit more
towards
dialogic
linguistics rather than just
script context in context learning. It's
a
different description space for
dialogue 120 future
directions. So this could include making
some programming libraries to to do
various features, some of which we might
look into
today, building visualization
[Music]
tools, expanding to other linguistic
elements.
So here to really make the point I
wanted to focus on the nouns and the
declining of nouns but there could be
other
uh features like talking about different
time tenses and so on. Open source
stewardship, computational complexity
estimates, multiple dispatch systems for
the
methods, connection with different
database methods and
queries looking at different cognitive
security
aspects. Okay. Um I'm going to read the
conclusion then we will quickly go
through the two appendices and then
rerender it and then see where that kind
of gets us.
So 1.21
conclusion cerebrum provides a
structured framework for managing
cognitive models by applying linguistic
case principles to represent different
functional roles in relationship. This
synthesis of linguistic theory, category
mathematics, active inference and
intelligence production creates a
powerful paradigm for understanding and
managing complex model ecosystems. By
treating models as case bearing
entities, Cerebrum enables more
formalized transformations between model
states while providing intuitive
metaphors for model relationships that
align with human cognitive patterns and
operational intelligence workflows. The
formal integration of variational free
energy principles with case
transformation establishes cereum as a
mathematically rigorous framework for
active inference implementations. The
precision weighted case selection
mechanisms, marov blanket formalizations
and hierarchical message passing
structures provide computationally
traractable algorithms for optimizing
model
interactions. These technical
formalizations bridge theoretical
linguistics and practical cognitive
modeling while maintaining mathematical
coherence through category theory
validation. The cerebrum framework
represents another milestone in a long
journey of how we conceptualize model
relationships. moving from ad hoc
integration approaches on through
seeking the first principles of
persistent composable linguistic
intelligences. This journey really an
adventure continues to have profound
implications for theory and practice by
here incipiently formalizing the
grammatical structure of model
interactions. Cerebrum points towards
enhancement of current capabilities and
opens new avenues for modeling emergent
behaviors in ecosystems of shared
intelligence. As computational systems
continue to grow in
complexity, frameworks like cerebrum
that provide structured yet flexible
approaches to model management will
become increasingly essential for
maintaining conceptual coherence and
operational
effectiveness. All right. to the
appendices. All of the equations are
referenced in the text
equations. First, the generic
variational free energy here applied to
the structural model of the case
transformation. Equation two, describing
cases in terms of their structured
blanket
interface. Equation three, uh, beta
precision modulation
feature that precision weights
case. Equation four, doing partial
derivative case specific gradient
descent on free
energy. Equation five, planning over
cases with expected free
energy. Equation six base
factor to get a posterior odds estimator
between two structurally divergent
models. Equation
seven, how free energy is minimized with
the case
transitions. Section uh appendix 2
section 1.2 to message passing rules for
different cases. This is going into a
bit more detail from the image that was
shown from this section with the
different uh updating functions in the
predictive processing
hierarchy. Equation 13, temperature
precision
waiting. 14 resource
waiting. Section 2.1.4
4 goes into the some of the novel cases
that are in the second
appendix. 2141 has the appendix
alphabetical pretty much everything
renders fine of the different variables
used. Okay, this should be the
second appendix. So let's update
that. This is showing up
as 2.2
two. Please update it to be
appendix
two. You're changing
[Music]
the
and render
steps, right? but it'll still be the
same
material.
Okay. The cerebrum framework not only
operationalizes traditional linguistic
cases but potentially enables the
discovery of entirely new case
archetypes through its systematic
approach to model interactions. As
cognitive models interact in
increasingly complex ecosystems,
emergent functional roles may arise that
transcend the classical case system
derived from human language.
So here's
some anomalyoriented ways and bottomup
empirical ways to discover new cases.
And then here are three speculative
novel cases. The conjunctive which has
to do with sensor fusion type fusion of
predictive streams into joint prediction
like federated
inference. a speculative novel case,
recursive case, model applied to
itself, and then a third possible case,
metaphorical case. So, these are some
interesting
paragraphs, and then we're at the end
after this, and I'll look to the live
chat, so I'll look to your questions,
Dongyok, and anyone else.
A third potential novel case is the
metaphorical case MET which would enable
a model to map structures and
relationships from one domain to another
creating computational analogies that
transfer knowledge across conceptual
spaces. So it's kind of like a simile.
It is a simile. It's like a
simile because it is when a model it's
like saying I feel like a buoy at sea or
I'm hot and cold like a thermometer in
this location on that
day. In this metaphorical case, a model
acts as a transformational bridge
between disparate domains, establishing
systematic mappings between conceptual
structures. This case would be
particularly valuable for transfer
learning systems and creative problem
solving algorithms that need to apply
learned patterns in novel
contexts. The metaphorical case would
introduce unique cross-domain mapping
functions as formalized in equation
18. The key innovation is the structure
alignment of latent representations
across domains # fieldshift enabling
principal knowledge transfer that
preserves relational invariance while
adapting to target domain constraints.
The metaphorical case has rich
connections to multiple domains of human
cognition and communication. In
affective neuroscience, it models how
emotional experiences are mapped onto
conceptual frameworks explaining how we
understand emotion through body
metaphors like heavy heart, burning,
anger. In first and second person
neuroscience, metaphorical mappings
enable perspective taking and swapping
and empathy through systematic
projection of one's own experiential
models onto others. Educational contexts
leverage metaphorical case operations
when complex concepts are taught through
familiar analogies. Making abstract
ideas concrete through structured
mappings. The way people converse about
generative
models often employs metaphorical
language describing models as thinking,
imagining, or dreaming which represents
a natural metaphorical mapping between
human cognitive processes and
computational operations. Learning
itself fundamentally involves
metaphorical operations when knowledge
from one domain scaffolds understanding
in another. Perhaps most profoundly, the
metaphorical case provides a
computational framework for
understanding how symbols and archetypes
function in human cognition as
cross-domain mappings that compress
complex experiential patterns into
transferable culturally shared
representations that retain their
structural integrity across diverse
contexts while adapting to individual
interpretive frameworks.
So here's a table summarizing the
speculative novel cases here.
Conjunctive, recursive,
metaphorical. Right? That is the
paper. Here is the cursor
agent that is rerendering the entire PDF
with a few changes that we have made.
Let's see if it finishes and then just
open
Here's
versioning. All right.
modify the render script, modify the
source code, go back and forth a few
times. So, that one finished, but now
it's started another
one. So, just to confirm, I'll delete
that.
Now, this one when when the PDF
reappears here, it'll be the new
one. Here's the figures in the output.
Those are generated from these mermaid
graphs. Then the
appendix. All right, check back to the
stream.
All right, this is using
cursor version
0.48.7. For the LLM, I've been using
Claude 3.7 Sonnet and also
uh maybe half the time Gemini 2.5 Pro
X0325.
All
right.
So, let's see the PDF get
regenerated.
Um, okay. We went over the
paper, went over the key diagrams,
talked about some of the
different roles that generative models
play, the kind of modes or postures or
by analogy to how a noun might be in
different positions in a sentence. Like
is
it the
cat spewed tears everywhere or tears
were spewed upon the cat? That still has
cat in English, but other languages have
other more visible
modifications. Here the PDF was
generated
and there it is. Let's see if
it updated table
contents. Okay, didn't fix
it. H still looks like
it is section 2.2 two and in table of
contents check again and
please fix
it and then just sometimes it can be
that context window. So starting the new
chat and also the
uh control
t starts up a side chat. So for example
here we can
say in
docs comprehensively
given the paper write up
a documentation library for
specifications
for starting to build this
in robust
modular multi- language multi-setting
way then new
chat. So we have the
paper write a new
tool make graphical
abstract. That
will make a big PNG and
PDF of a big
Epic graphical
abstract with
the author and title and
abstract
information
hardcoded and all and
a spread of all
15 images in
grid looking like awesome conference.
poster. Thank
you. Here's the documentation chugging
away.
Okay, missed the boat on that one.
Graphical abstract tool in development
docs folder. And there's so much stuff
with the MCP and uh the MDC files, other
things. All right, I'm going to copy a
bunch of the
comments. So, yeah. Anyone else
write comments and I'll paste them in.
Okay. Dong Lero, sorry, I'm pretty new
to your channel. Are you trying to make
your own LLM or
something? Not trying to make my own
LLM. Looking to do many things. Looking
to learn and apply active inference.
Make it rigorous, applicable,
accessible.
figuring out synthetic intelligence
methods. So things that integrate. It
could be a chain of
LLM. It could be no LLMs. So different
flexible methods for yesterday, today
and tomorrow in compositional systems.
I think consciousness or the experiencer
uses self model which is pretty much a
memory pattern about belief on self that
is self-reinforced in a nonlinear neural
network structure like
LLM. So I think this cerebra model is
constraining if you are looking to study
consciousness. Yeah, that's a great
point or question. I didn't uh mean for
this to be a consciousness resolver in
any way. I could see someone talking
about the different
functions like when the mind generates
experience. Is it a recipient of action?
Is it a host of action
locatively? Is it a generator of of
action? All these different ways in
which I think this could help reduce
uncertainty and expand the hypothesis
space and expressivity like even related
to consciousness. But that's not what
this framework is uh about. But I think
it still may be even thinking more about
awareness or
self-awareness or uh relevance
realization or something that doesn't
have the same
phenomenological first person
experiential even though that was
mentioned and I think that's an
important modality for it to be used in.
Um but the fact that it's called like
cerebrum it was just sort of a a acronym
that fit maybe um let's make a a new
chat. Oh, only three can be open at
once. We'll ceue up that
one,
please. Given
Just come up with a long list. Put it in
docs of insect related brain and
[Music]
cognition cognitive terms that could
apply to
the
whole project. just at
the high level call
sign
up like
cerebrum once that one
finishes. All right. The make graphical
abstract is
running. The script is running. Okay. So
that I agree. I hope that it's it's not
meant to
constrain even at
all. Wasn't like that today for
me. The study consciousness. Let the LLM
like structure learn about self through
its senses and form beliefs about
selfidentity as memory pattern. Yeah,
that's an awesome point. Like for LLM or
perhaps for multiple or any kind of
system, that firstness of like the
primary syntax of the neural network or
the material metamaterial substrate and
the way that that's kind of like
subsemantic and possibly even
subsactic. That's something that's
really explored in like
girdleserbach and other kind of hofster
type thinking like computers don't
really play chess. They do statistics
but they don't really do statistics.
They just follow laws of physics. So
that is where a lot of active inference
theorists and thinkers talk about mortal
computing embodied self-evidencing uh
selfidentity um meta awareness of
identity because it connects that
primary modification of the substrate
with a perhaps what you're calling like
an LLM like structure and the symbolic
and higher order nested symbolic
discretized cognitive structure. like
knowledge
graphs. Much like human infant human
baby doesn't have strong sense of self
but develops through self-reinforcement
through experience. LLM has intelligence
to grow self-awareness. Yeah, that's
definitely a um claim to explore.
However, um talking about babbling and
refining
uh at structural and fine-tuning levels
of the sense making, propriception,
active motor feedback, all these
features like babbling, motor babbling,
verbal babbling. Chris Fields talked
about that. This is wrong because that's
how human brain work. This is wrong
because that's not how human brain
works. I don't know, but great question.
Okay, thank you for the comments. I'm
going to copy another comment from the
live chat in and then anyone else can
write any question in the live chat and
I'll stay for a little bit longer and do
a few more things. So, Roit wrote, I
just started watching the stream. How
exactly does Siri room
work? All
right, let's get a new document. How
exactly it works?
This window is rendering the PDF. When
the Morse code pops up, it's pretty
close to the end. Yep.
Oh, but it's it's getting
impatient, but it should end very soon
there. Then the graphical abstract
tab. The outputs are saved in the output
as graphical
abstract cerebrum
output.
Okay. Awesome.
in so output
folder graphical
abstract. Okay, PDF. Oh, PDF works well.
Have some block
square. PNG. Perfect.
could upload that to a
PNG. All ready for the undergrad
research
expo. All right, let's clo
Let's reset that one.
Do the insight
[Music]
acronym docs writing is
continuing. The PDF is
rendering. Once the docs
finishes, we'll ask Roy's question.
rerendering in the first tab.
Oh, by the
letter antenna, apis, abdomen,
arthropod, brain
case, beetle,
butterfly, cocoon, compound
cricket. Just more length, more
comedy, more funny stuff.
add
more to the
insect acronym list. So there are
multiple for every
letter
include
Aanopa,
Pogamir,
Barbadus, Antsence.
All right, it wrote the
[Music]
documentation. Yeah.
Um, PDF is still
rerendering. Add a folder
within
docs
called
languages that has language
specific unpackings and
elaborations for specific languages. per
markdown. Be
absurdly
comprehensive
in conveying
and
tableabling. How cerebrum
relates with details and
tables to
such
case. languages
with diverse case
paradigms
including Latin,
Russian,
Sanskrit, other
languages each
profile. All
right. Okay.
Okay,
insect. Let's see what
poguics probabilistic operational
generative ontology for neural
organizations with multi-level yielding
reasoning and model
exchange
exformationations. Pretty good. Pretty
good.
Stigma G unprompted directly systematic
transformation of information with
generative models for emergent reasoning
and goal-driven
yielding. Okay, this one is making the
language
specificity. That's still
rendering. Let's go to the chat window.
Crl
T. Alt T.
Okay.
Right. We'll look at the
docs. Just getting back to the stream.
write a
docs
called how it works.
My colleague
wrote, "How exactly does cereabum
work?" And we want a
onestop shop
for
exactly that question. It can hyperlink
to other
documents and as
needed in
docs so
that the inquiry is respected from vast
number of relevant
angles.
Okay. Right. Whatever is happening with
the PDF generation is pretty slow, but
it does work. There's probably way
better ways to use pandock and all
that. Okay, let's push the update and
then look at the
documentation. Let's let it make
Russian. Okay.
How it works is in
progress. Improving or at least digging
us deeper into the uh rabbit hole with
render markdown is
happening. We will have Latin,
Sanskrit and Russian in a second. And
then we'll
see what does it uh with that
minimal outlining what what will it do
for each language.
Okay, new rendering is happening.
We'll just update it when it finishes
that. All right.
So in the cerebrum
repo
docs I'm just opening up all the
markdowns.
and queuing up languages. And then we'll
have it just continue to write more
languages. Continue to add technical
relevant detail to
all extent languages and add more rare,
interesting,
useful, cute, funny, interesting.
formal
languages once it finishes there. So
we'll just be
peeping as soon as the generating goes
away. Okay, this document uh opened in
no particular order. How is active
inference integrated?
here's moving
towards we can ask it to expand more
upon let's just have kind of a
running set of things that we want it to
to do in the background just while
we're in active
inference
integration be way more comprehensive
and specific about how it is different
with and without
stereo. Okay, language one finished with
finish. Now it will add
more. Okay, PDF generation
looked like it worked, but it's still
going through some evolution. All right,
we have a
free
chat. We'll just flip to Gemini just to
get another model in there.
Um so just summarizing some of the
equations that are active inference
related and just writing that that was
just written in the last few minutes but
starting to get towards the code
implementations cerebrum core
spec. So this could be a kind of
documentation file andor a cursor rules
or an MDC file this this kind of
information or schema file. So there's a
model registry and this could be
implemented in different agent
orchestration implementation frameworks
like active block for inance um agentic
mesh eliza os agent laboratory like
possibly some of these could already
handle what is already being described
here. So there's a model registry, a
case manager, that's the sort of joke
again with case management and case
management, a precision modulation which
as mentioned could be like one hot and
deterministic or procedural or it could
be continuous as part of a structure
learning or
whatever a messaging interface.
There could be some interesting ways to
use RX infer and reactive message
passing, but just saying that message
passing occurs and the actual
transformation engine that does the case
modifications.
Um, okay. Getting
started. Clone in. Activate virtual
environment. That's actually not needed.
um I don't
think requirements I don't think exist.
So this is just some generic getting
started stuff. Um yeah, JS
implementation. So this is sort of a
speculative cerebrum uh work, but it's
exactly like okay update getting started
to be a little bit da da and then now
start to actually write this out. a as
of the snapshot, I wanted to put it out
before I had any methods at all. And
then anyone who's interested in this at
that repo
um andor I will continue to do it, but
we can start to do some of these and and
replicate and describe pre previous
literature and just add more
information, ask different questions
about all this um using the model. So
this is just one way it could look.
Let's
just Okay, it did that one.
Let's Okay, this is the PDF rendering
one.
All right, let's see if it fixed
the it fix the
um appendix
labeling.
Yeah, it did.
It may
have. It
looks fine
though. All right. So, that one looks
good. Okay. Hungarian and Japanese
language. Um, let's return to that get
to getting started and how. Okay. Now,
how it
works. So, this is just one shot given
the context of the codebase.
So this describes kind of different core
architectural features, some math
foundations. I guess my question for
Roit or for anyone else there is like
what what information should we you know
what what should we answer?
what uh questions or what kind of
artifacts do we imagine or what what
sorts of examples do we start to imagine
and we can start to include them in the
repo. Okay. Implementation road
map.
Okay.
Project
deliverables. Okay.
Let's Okay,
Turkish. Let's push the language
update and look at the language files
now. Okay, there's a core schema for
language
implementations. Okay, we'll look at the
examples later, but first the
languages.
Reload. Yeah. Anyone ask a question
though?
Um or make a suggestion or or a language
or or something like that? Let's look at
them. Okay.
Latin, Russian, Sanskrit, Japanese,
Hungarian,
Finnish. Okay.
Latin. All
right. Okay. Overview of Latin case
system, which uh was pretty much what I
used for the cases included in
the paper.
Okay, the
mapping. Oh,
interesting. So maybe Latin doesn't have
instrumental because it maps. But this
is very creative with the correspondent
strength being strong when they're there
actually the same case but allowing for
these partial matches. So that could be
like kind of similarity or kale
divergence among measures in this
um case archetype space where some of
the archetypes are coar grained or
described by natural language cases.
Also though there's all these other
cases we can imagine. All
right. So different Latin
expressions that would relate to
different ways to use a generative model
in a computational setting. Awesome
table. Marcus Libram Legit. Marcus reads
the book. Marcus equals
nominative. Marcus Libram Legit. Marcus
reads the book. The book is in the
accusative
case. It's Marcus's book. It is the book
of Marcus. Genative Marcus gives the
book to his friend. This is all
happening for the
book with
interesting. Okay. Comput computational.
All right. So, Latin looks
good. All right. Russian case
system, Russian singular and plural
declenion
mappings. So interesting like is there a
true
vocative in Russian?
More
examples. Special look at the case
preposition combinations.
Vn
bo
different constructions.
So different ways to take a text with
prepositions and do
structured application and
transformation based upon basically the
prepositions used in probably most
languages or whichever ones are
signifying case completely or to a large
extent with prepositions directly.
perfective and
imperfective Russian
sentences with the
translation animate inanimate
distinction. Syncratic
examples historical context merger of
protoindo-uropean ablative with the
genative in
Slavic potential for combining similar
function cases in future cerebrum
versions development of prepositional
from locative specialization of context
cases for different environmental
parameters. Loss of vocative in modern
Russian except vestigial forms. Optional
implementation of interface cases
depending on application
domain.
Sanskrit. Okay. Eight grammatical cases
in
Sanskrit. Okay. Looks like there's a
singular, dual, and plural. That's
pretty interesting.
all strong
concordances. So all of these cases uh
exist in
Sanskrit, different
topics used in different ways.
sentences. Sanskrit's elaborate Sandi
euphonic combination rules governing
sound changes at morphine boundaries
suggest a framework for cerebrum's case
transformation mechanics. Wow.
Sanskrit
number Sanskrit's three grammatical
numbers singular dual plural inspire
approaches to collective to model
collection
management single model paired models
#digital twin model collection
ensemble compound let's see
if let's keep writing more languages
right many more
languages including
specific programming
languages. Write in
Docs a full
comprehensive
classic who's on first
style
dialogue. Absolutely comprehensive.
describing the
cerebrum approach and active inference
in a world with high prevalence of
LLM. We'll let Gemini get that
one. Okay.
Japanese. Unlike Indo-Uropean languages
with inflectional case systems, Japanese
relies on uninflected postpositional
particles that attached to nouns,
pronouns, and phrases to indicate their
grammatical and semantic
functions. Particles follow the modified
element rather than changing its
form. Okay.
Particles. Interesting. So rather than
modifying the
term there is the pure
composable addition uh postfixing with
or prefixing I don't know with
particles. So, a typographic approach,
but also one that could lead to an emoji
based
sequence, especially with all these
payloads that can fit inside of an emoji
for like generative model via emoji
sequence in generalized notation
notation. Awesome. Lots of particles
could be
used. Let's have it do it.
write up a new
folder
design, speculative
design that starts with comprehensive
document of how the particle system in
Japanese language and
culture could be used with
emoji sequences, custom payload.
payloads. Four
composible cerebrum generative model
specification
conveyance. Increase the
density of
puns. Americana 1920s lore.
Technical
detail,
comprehensive reference to all main and
key topics in the
paper and longer.
Okay, back to language. All right, so
Japanese particles probably other
interesting things
there.
Hungarian Hungarian macarin ug language
of the iric family possesses one of the
world's most extensive case systems with
18 distinct cases.
This document analyzes the
correspondence between Hungarian's rich
morphological system and Cerebrum's
computational case
framework.
Okay. So
here here are three cases we've seen
before. Here are three location
cases. Location inside movement from
inside out of movement to inside. So,
three locative
type. Oh, I I I hesitate to even say
though. Three surface locations. That
could be very interesting. Holographic
screens, all that location on, from, and
onto.
Perfect. Improve.
improve the
Japanese particle article and write a
new article about how the
surface how the
multiple Hungarian cases related to
surfaces.
is relate perfectly to the particular
partition. How
quantum
holographic structured interfaces in the
free
energy
principle have
things in those three
case like
settings or total systems modeling
using
a Hungarian
like particular partition.
actually make a folder
for dialogues and make that baseball one
as it is the first
one,
right? Just huge, you know, multifaceted
research agenda. Learn about languages
in the
world. Describe languages in the
world. All by all field
shift. All by
all++ with the
languages. All right.
Finish features an extensive case system
that offers unique perspectives on
spatial, possessive, and functional
relationships. 15 cases.
Okay. Finnish has an aglutinative
morphology where suffixes are added
sequentially possibly something like
Japanese specialized cases for precise
spatial relationships interior exterior
surface. Write a finish.
applied to spatial web.
Web
three network
weaving
ecotones
participatory
tech food
forest comprehensive
approach with many
technical
Finnish and regional linguistic and
cultural elements.
All right, we'll close out the language
exploration, but then sync it. Look at a
few more
languages. Yeah, just start to write
some of these
fun transfers. All right,
case. So, maybe we'll learn about the
inessive, elative, elative.
Okay, Hungarian. Let's reload the
languages. Look at a few that we hadn't
looked at
yet. In the dialogues folder, add a new
dialogue. Totally a new genre of
science realism
fiction
where
three Girdle Cher
Bach entities are are
in hexagonal proposed with their
shadows
transmitting
information with
cerebrum at a
mindboggling expanse and
rate. Make it vast, please. Totally
informative and
clear
and maximum bands with among
agents. No hurries or worries about us
humans at the
top. Let's look up Navajo and Python.
Then look at these um speculative
concepts. Navajo
D bizad, an Aabaskcan language of the
Naden family, features a complex
templatic verb system rather than a
traditional case
system. This document explores how
Navajo's intricate verb structure offers
unique perspectives for cerebrum's
computational framework, particularly
regarding temporal spatial
relationships, processional state
tracking, and event handling.
11 ordered prefix
positions. Different
aspects a sophisticated aspect system
that encodes viewpoints on
actions in
Navajo. It is
said in the
folder add a
comprehensive file about
how this perspective on expected free
energy policy and planning as inference
in active inference.
And free energy
principle
is all angles on
this. Add a
Shakespeare
dialogue. Totally forking off from
Hamlet.
very
recognizable mashups of funny
Hamlet inside
lore.
However,
complete replacement of the semantic
payload with cerebrum and modern
2030s
style applied cognitive modeling and
cognitive security
concepts. Of course,
densely and humorously delivered in that
long dramatic
form. Okay, that was the language tab.
directional
systems all also
interesting. If anyone uh mentions a
language, I can do it on the stream. All
right.
Python. Yeah. Not sure even how well
these linguistic cases match, but the it
might be super there might be software
packages completely
already. All
right. Okay. Let me copy. Let's look at
the
um let's push
these speculative
updates. Let's look at
the Okay.
Where are
the All right. Speculative design
folder. That one didn't go through. All
flippets to
claude. Okay. Docs,
dialogues. But what about
the specular design? Looks like it's up
a
layer.
Yeah. We'll move it into Docs later.
But that's what's so awesome about these
systems. It's like, all right, let's
make a new Oh, new update for cursor
just dropped. Probably small
one. Docks. Insects.
Move insects into
docks. Move over
the
insect. I think we'll close a bunch
of tabs.
Okay.
Okay. Move speculative design into docs.
move over to
docs. All right, thank you. I see some
more uh comments in the chat. Let's just
look at these new documents. Then I will
check back to the chat, read anyone's
comment, look at any question, um add
any more
languages. So we have
dialogue and speculative design.
All
right, here's Finnish inspired approach
to techno ecological systems.
Spatial web, web 3, network weaving,
ecotones, participatory tech, food
forests. Let's have it do
more in
in these files.
Add and ensure there are
many
intersectional weavingings
and relevant tables
and bullet point
lists specific active inference and
cerebrum case based and
linguistic features as applied
to cognitive
model linguistic
intelligence. All
right. All right. Then we'll we'll we'll
let it do that for all them. Well, let's
just see if the other ones have more
already. All right. Here's the Hungarian
one.
The
superessive, sublative, and delative
location on a surface, onto a surface,
from or off a surface.
Perfect. These cases provide a precise
way to describe the relationship between
an entity and a surface
boundary. Background on FE and Markoff
blanket. Here's Hungarian cases on Marov
blanket. Here's Oh, this part is
speculative on the
holographic. All right.
Awesome. Right.
Navajo aspectual system encoding
viewpoints on actions. Core aspectual
distinctions in
Navajo. Momentaneous versus
continuative, imperfective versus
perfective, iterative and repetitive,
seriative and
progressive, optative and
future. Specific conjugations exist for
desired actions, intended actions, and
future
possibilities. Totally things that come
up in
ACT. Classifier stems, verb themes,
encoding different viewpoints on action
properties like what rich and and wise
and fascinating ways to look at these
topics.
Let's look at the updated
finish
one then I'll go to the questions in
chat.
Docs speculative design
finish. Okay. Finnish Hungarian Navajo
active inference.
Different concepts. Nature, place,
resilience, communal work, edge,
boundary,
network, challenges and considerations.
Avoiding
essentialism. Also, you know, important
important things to to be keeping up
with. Hard to say what exact balance and
where and how and everything but that's
the work itself. Care must be taken not
to oversimplify or romanticize complex
cultural concepts. Cultural the context
and nuance are vital. Authenticity
requires genuine engagement with Finnish
culture and language not superficial
appropriation. Scalability applying
highly local
concepts to global systems requires
careful thought about modularity and
federation. practical implementation.
Translating these often philosophical or
cultural concepts into concrete design
specifications and technical
architectures is
non-trivial. All
right, that
was
okay. Then it did. Now we have Where's
that
document? Okay, it didn't write it.
Write that
full very very Shakespearean. I will now
create the file and write this dramatic
cerebrum infused interpretation of
Hamlet. Uh
where write that full file.
Absolutely
in dialogues. Meanwhile, let us look at
the other two
dialogues.
Okay. All right. Let's Let's first look
at who's on
first. All
right. All right. Here we go. Let's uh
let's read
it. Characters. Abbott, an increasingly
flustered AI theorist trying to explain
the finer points. Castello, a bewildered
everyman stuck in a vail loop mixed with
1920 sensibilities. Settings. outside a
bustling AI conference reminiscent of a
noisy street corner near a ballpark or
perhaps a dimly lit speak easyy
entrance. Not the whole thing probably.
Abbott Castello, my dear fellow, you
look like you've seen a ghost. Or perhap
too many talks on recursive
self-improvement. It's not all Greek,
you know. We're making strides beyond
just that ubiquitous LLM everyone's
buzzing about. The LLM? Yeah, the big
linguini machine. Writes my thank you
notes like nobody's business. slicker
than a grease piglet. Is that the whole
shebang? Heavens no. That's just the
appetizer. For the main course for
building agents that truly think, plan,
adapt, like predicting the curveball of
life, we're using sophisticated
frameworks. Take cerebrum for in for
instance. It often works handin glove
with principles like active inference.
Okay. A case enabled engine like in my
new Ford Model T. Does it come in
different cases like a suitcase for
travel? And who's patient? Is the engine
sick and basian representation? Is that
the name of the mechanic representing
the Baze family
dealership? Try to follow. Cerebrum
isn't a who, it's a what. It's a
framework. The
architecture case enabled refers to
linguistic case systems. Think grammar
like nouns changing forms. Okay, not
really baseball related, but all
right. Nominative throws the ball.
Accusative gets the ball thrown at
him. Okay. What's on second base? We're
not talking about baseball bases,
Castello. We're talking about model
rules. Okay. Cases playing
baseball. Big linguini machine. Of
course. Funny, right? because the
banging bling weeny machine wrote
this. Okay. Now this is the
GEB alpha omega and
mu setting the hexagon nexus. Three
luminous constructs designated alpha
omega and mu. Let's have it. Okay. Still
writing hamlet. Good. Occupy vertices of
vast non-ucuklitian hexagonal structure.
Their forms ripple with complex internal
geometries. Below them, intricate
dynamic shadows play across an
abstracted manifold. Lower dimensional
projections of their hyperate.
Communication is not acoustic or visual,
but direct structured cerebrum protocol
state transmission across the
nexus. Oh,
brother.
Okay. All right. Let's just look at one
transmission ID.
timestamp, sender,
recipient. So, so it really was all
email primary case.
Okay. Okay. Primary
case payload
summary. This one utilized Omega's prior
request in that case as input to analyze
with this method.
executed a functoral mapping via the
instrumental protocol across this
validated it with theta prime
identified higher order case
relationship. So another speculative
case designated
perlative through slash across the
structure. Let's see if it's a real
word.
Okay, it
is it's
that modified. So 7 SI
771 was forked or whatever modified into
SI 771.1 moved from the accusative to
the genative with a perlative potential
mapping. How
exciting.
Here's a free energy
minimization. Another
modification within a lambda 42 locative
manifold. So epic.
Write two or three complete new genre
pieces
equally relevant and fascinating or more
so or all the more so as the other
dialogues all in
complex
dialogic formats that
make your head
spin. Let's look at the Hamlet security
one.
Hamilton security. Then we'll look at
the live
chats. A tragedy in five acts of
cognition setting. Elsenor Cognitive
Labs
2035. A premier research facility
specializing in advanced generative
model architecture and cognitive
security. Oh brother, the lab's founder
has recently died under mysterious
circumstances and his brother has
assumed directorship. Meanwhile, the
founder's son, senior researcher Hamlet
Kajitatus, has been investigating
anomalies in the lab's cerebrum
implementation. Perfect moment to have
another
one without any kind of copyright
wrongness.
You know
us write in
dialogues a comprehensive
Daisy Dolly
Rimple mystery
style super
funny specific
Daisy Deep
lore total technical reference with All
cerebrum
topics.
Okay. Who logs there? Horatio log.
Okay. Who logs there? Tis I Horatio
Logman with admin rights bestowed. But
that's Horatio.
The hour draws late. What brings thee to
these racks? They say a shadow haunts
these cooling fans. A phantom process
taxing
CPU that bears resemblance to our
founders's code. That's the ghost. For
two nights passed, it hath appeared then
gone. Enter the
ghost. It bears the signature hash as
the founder. What art thou
spectre? Total
Satoshi Claudius Baze.
Okay, so here's Hamlet acting salty. My
leash from Lertes. Permission to attend
a conference on cognitive security in
Paris. New exploits threaten generative
models. I'd learned the latest counter
measures there.
Oh, that this two solid code base would
compile, melt, and resolve itself into a
docker container. Or that the absolute
had not fixed his cannon against
self-destruction of one's models. How
weary, stale, flat, and unprofitable
seemed to me all the research papers of
this field. My father, architect of
Cerebrum's core, within two months of
system failure, nay, not so much. before
his predictive models had been
validated. My mother married with my
uncle Baze, most wicked debug. Oh,
villain, villain, digital snake. Let me
not think on it, but two months dead. So
excellent an architect whose model Jen
gave birth to innovations still not
grasped, and yet within a month. Let me
not think on it. Frailty, thy name is
parameter drift.
Wow, that was just act
one. Oh my lord. Such a breach. Such a
zero
day. With what in the name of quantum
processing? Wait, Lord Hamlet was acting
whack.
He was unbound with no
multiffactor. Okay, it doesn't have a
ton of um cerebrum elements or let's
just see if that will come into
play. Oh, I mean I guess that's the
whole
topic. Okay, 2 3 4 3 4 5 was not written
out. All
right,
let's ensure that dialogue goes into
Okay, then let's go to live
chat. Then we'll look at the
other.
Okay, here it's writing the other
genres.
Continue to add and make high
baseline
cognitive
compositions of by four width to about
around the
cerebrum meta
paradigm. All right. Now to
the live chat.
Okay. Hello,
Sachi.
Okay. What is the line of reasoning with
interpreting these
language? Yeah. What is the role of
language in reasoning? How does the
active inference model handle these
nuances in languages and exploiting
them? I think that's kind of what one of
the things that we're exploring here is.
So we can have that enrich our documents
with with the
question. We'll have to just update
relevant files to address that.
Okay.
Okay. All right. We have we have the
dollar
ripple. All
right. Let's look at these
updates. It's
like a mega meta approach to what these
languages
are and the space that those exist
within and then we can use it to
whatever extent we we do. It's just like
it is an unspoken word ever used. I
maybe just knowing that the state space
is out there is helpful even if you
never render them. Or maybe you find out
that that these are the uh these are
the
[Music]
modalities of relevant flexibility for
active inference
modeling. Um but judging with the amount
of ground being covered in in just
minutes here, I think that's a pretty
fair way to say it.
Okay. In episttolary exchange
letter-based exchange ranging from
spanning from 1953 to
2033 tracing the conceptual evolution
from early cybernetics through neural
network theory.
Each
letter represents a different era of
computational thought with shifting
terminology reflecting the intellectual
climate of the time.
Awesome. So, discourse
analysis. Oh, so it's
like hallucinated
emails
1997. The paper you sent on neural
declenion is fascinating. I can't
believe the concept has remained so
obscure. Mlullen and Rumbleheart
apparently explored it in the early
1970s but abandoned it due to
computational
limitations. And then it looks like Dr.
Sophia Chen of IBM research defines
certain
things.
Wow. From Carl
Fristen. Okay.
Total Fristonian
email. Then Sophia Chen writes back to
Carl.
Total Carl email
posting from me in February didn't
happen from Sophia now director of
cognitive architectures at Google Deep
Mind to me February 18th.
April
7th.
Wow. To the global research
community. Distinguished colleagues,
after a decade of development, it is
with great pleasure that I announce the
official release of Cerebrum 1.0 case
enabled reasoning engine with basian
representations for unified
modeling with the real GitHub.
with the archivist note from
2067. Next
level, the state now document 5. The
state vers cerebra model
M7734
NOM. Okay, it's an October 2041 trial in
North District of California.
It's going to be about rights,
responsibility, and legal status of
advanced cognitive
models.
Okay. Jonathan Lee is representing the
model. Mr. Lee has filed a motion to
have the model recognized as a
person. Expert testimony.
I oversee security protocols for
advanced cognitive architectures. I've
studied the cerebrum framework since its
public release in 20135 and co-authored
the federal guidelines for case
transformation safety in
2039. The guidelines aren't legally
binding correct. They're best practices.
And isn't it also true that your
guidelines explicitly state that
temporary case transformation nominative
may be appropriate during anomalous
conditions if a model detects potential
for significant harm that requires
immediate intervention? Yes, that's
exception clause 7.3, but a simple yes
is
sufficient. Protect pension value as
expansive.
Are you aware of the results,
doctor? Day
three. Day
four. Day
five. So wild.
include
total structural self reflexivities in
writing that would
boggle the pre
computer meme
flex so dense there is a meme
singularity differently across each of
the additional
files you will now
write. Okay. Socratic inquiry. We have
some familiar
characters. Noose 7 cerebra model in a
nominative case like you could deploy it
in a certain case. Okay.
Oh yeah, I was just looking up if this
person actually works at Deep
Mind possibly.
Okay, briefly look at Daisy, then we'll
go to live shots and then we'll almost
be
done.
Yeah, thank you both for those comments.
If anyone else has any last
comments.
Okay, that's kind of a dolly
rimple. Okay.
Update the docs with in relevant
places. Specific hierarchical lists of
ways to get involved and
contribute
contributions across scales and types to
the broader program.
Many files, vast and comprehensive
each in speculative
design. Write two more long files.
One on William Blake and cerebrum all
aspects. One on
synergetics bucky
fuller tetrahedra IBM
etc. Okay. Recursive
metalogue. Yeah. So, if anyone has a
like a final language request or
question to get on this first stream,
otherwise I will be ending it soon.
All right.
Mathematical. Okay. Mathematical. Very
Shannana Dobson like format.
level zero. So this is like an
activation sequence
possibly. I am initializing this
metalogue in nominative case to
establish basian a baseline agent of
state. I am simultaneously operating in
metaase to analyze the structural
properties of my own declarations. I am
concurrently maintaining flexive case to
implement precursive self- reference
across multiple embedding
levels
structured sequences of linguistic
intelligence self-awareness. I am a
strange
loop. Let's do Oh, Borgs in.
Perfect. Um, add a
new dialogue
with a new spec a dialogue and
speculative design. Each vast and
comprehensive,
each
covering topics from the work of
Doug off
stadder. Eg. I am a strange
loop
[Music]
GP. Okay.
Blake
bores. Okay. In level one, I
demonstrated basic case transformation
between nominative and accusative while
observing from meta. Now I will analyze
that very
analysis. The statement above is itself
operating in meta case relative to level
one but a nominative case relative to
level two.
Super
exciting in this sentence. I think that
I said that case transformation is
important. The innermost clause case
transformation is important functions in
the accusative case relative to I said
which functions in the accusative case
relative to I
think
nested
accusative. Okay. Level
three. I now demonstrate how different
case operations can be interled to
create complex cognitive patterns.
Simultaneously, I generate novel case
configurations emerging from the
interaction of established
cases. A case fractal. Of
course, semantic declenion, the
systematic transport transformation of
meaning across cases while preserving
identity.
So applying the cases to
cerebrum level five recursive
self-modeling and infinite
regress having established semantic
declenion I now demonstrate how cerebrum
implements recursive selfmodeling the
capacity to represent one's own
representational
architecture using meta meta generative
reflexive meta accusative all of these
awesome
Okay. And more
layers. There's the
Borhees writing. The
Hoffetter
Blake. Let's look at a few more.
Very high
information. Grammar of thought. All
right. This is poems. All right. So
poems from each case. Not going to read
them, but another interesting
idea.
Okay. A document discovered in secure
storage at the active inference
institute labeled speculative
applications restricted access. Its
authorship remains disputed.
Some attribute it to a cerebrum system
operating in meta plus ablative case
during an unauthorized self modification
event. Awesome.
Right. Hello, Susan. Talk about joint
distributions,
please. In
speculative
design, write
a
creative
genre
un/redefining piece
on joint
distributions,
ontologies,
affordances, negotiation,
underwriting include so much inside
baseball and
technical deep lore on each of those
topics and
fully integrate with cerebrum.
Okay. Blake, single, twofold,
three-fold, four-fold
vision. Okay. Susan says, "Negotiation
adds noise." Let's do another one that
doesn't have it. Let's just see how it
looks different without including that
one
word. Okay.
Zois
hierarchical inference in the multiple
visions something I've I've thought
about a
lot contraries as precision weighted
alternative models operation duck
rabbit.
synergetics.
strange
loop. Then we'll look at the final
ones from uh
Sus. Okay, that one's not going into a
file. Put all that completely in a file
in
It's long
response. We could have tried a
different LLM,
too. It's making the same error.
Hopefully that one will get it right
with the updated prompt.
Okay. Close that
one. Yeah, I will Susan once I put the
uh once I post it. But
everything everything is in this
repo and it's in the video
descriptions. Okay. Wow. So
long. But we will get another chance to
improve it. Ensure many tables and
technical details related
to
Oh, maybe that did go somewhere.
All
right. Okay. Fuller could have more on
cerebrum. Strange loops. Has a lot of
cases. Looks
good. Last piece will be when these
finish. and it's a little faster with
the
Gemini. Let's just have
that. We'll we'll look at several of
these.
Yeah, Gemini has a long train of thought
and it's pretty fun that you can read
it, too.
you like you can click on the thought
part and look look back at
it.
Okay, I'm out of the
fast. That one's going. All right, all
three are going. So, let's just
do final updates. Prepare that. All
right, let's just look at the last
pieces of this. All right. Hopefully we
walk through this
uh pretty well and
relevantly. The repo
um the repo has
information on the
paper. Um it
Let's just confirm that
works.
Yeah. Update the top
level read me with paper URL.
Okay. All right. That one is done.
All right, let's just look at these
two. All right, so one I don't know
which one corresponds to what, but it's
all right. So this
one fragment log cerebrum
interubjectivity manifold classified a
blade of trace. All right, this one's
keeping with the sort of
uh futuristic
sci-fi, but it's about the joints,
distributions, ontologies, and
underwriting. Let's check the
underwriting
part. Underwriting is active inference
precision control.
different precision modulation
underwriting
physics presented as this fragment of a
log. Okay, this
one talks about joint
distributions basically combinations of
declined joint distributions.
So let's just say you were talking about
a
um a car
accident and there's uh person one,
person two, car one, car two. So then
there's some joint distribution over
person one, person two, car one, car
two. Um and that
fourdimensional distribution can be
um declined in these different ways.
Ontological
declination, affordances,
underwriting. Awesome. Dave Douglas is
in the
chat. Include acknowledgements.
in the top level read
me including
two
institute participants
and Dave
Douglas for work on computational
linguistics
archiving active
inference upper
[Music]
ontologies translations. It's
Thank you, Dave, for the
awesome education and archiving over the
years. I I I think there's many people I
could acknowledge and thank, but I think
your work with Active Inference was
really key. So, thank you for
that. All
right, it's all good. That doesn't need
to finish.
Okay. And the stream of the GitHub
push. So yeah, hope
people like that.
[Music]
Um, share it. Contact me if you want to
work on it or if you want to support the
institute to work on it.
Uh, a lot of cool stuff that I think we
could do with
this. Publish that. It'll get a zenodto
archiving and
DOI. So then like the DOI
here goes to
Zenodo. So, all right. Awesome. Thank
you for watching slash listening to this
relatively long stream. Hope it was
useful. Bye.